<story-context id="bmad/bmm/workflows/4-implementation/story-context" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>10</epicId>
    <storyId>10-4</storyId>
    <title>WCAG Accessibility Compliance</title>
    <status>drafted</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-11-25</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/stories/10-4-wcag-accessibility-compliance.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>

  <story>
    <asA>user with disabilities</asA>
    <iWant>the application to be accessible</iWant>
    <soThat>I can use it with assistive technologies</soThat>
    <tasks>
      <task>Accessibility audit using testing tools (axe DevTools, WAVE, Lighthouse)</task>
      <task>Fix keyboard navigation (all interactive elements accessible via keyboard)</task>
      <task>Add ARIA labels and roles for screen readers</task>
      <task>Ensure proper heading hierarchy and semantic HTML</task>
      <task>Add text alternatives for color-coded information</task>
      <task>Ensure sufficient color contrast ratios</task>
      <task>Fix form labels and error messages</task>
      <task>Test with screen readers and keyboard navigation</task>
    </tasks>
  </story>

  <acceptanceCriteria>
    <criterion id="AC1">
      <given>I use assistive technologies</given>
      <when>I navigate the application</when>
      <then>it: Meets WCAG 2.1 Level AA standards, Works with screen readers, Has keyboard navigation, Has text alternatives for colors, Has clear form labels</then>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC2">
      <given>I navigate using only keyboard</given>
      <when>I use the application</when>
      <then>I can: Access all interactive elements, Navigate between sections, Submit forms, Use all features, See focus indicators</then>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC3">
      <given>I use a screen reader</given>
      <when>I navigate the application</when>
      <then>I can: Understand page structure, Navigate by headings, Understand form labels, Understand button purposes, Understand error messages</then>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC4">
      <given>I have color vision deficiency</given>
      <when>I view the application</when>
      <then>I can: Understand all information without relying on color alone, See text alternatives for color-coded information, Distinguish interactive elements</then>
    </criterion>
  </acceptanceCriteria>

  <artifacts>
    <docs>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/epics.md</path>
        <title>Epic Breakdown</title>
        <section>Epic 10: Mobile Optimization &amp; Polish - Story 10.4</section>
        <snippet>As a user with disabilities, I want the application to be accessible, So that I can use it with assistive technologies. WCAG 2.1 Level AA compliance, keyboard navigation, screen reader support, color contrast.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/PRD.md</path>
        <title>Product Requirements Document</title>
        <section>Accessibility</section>
        <snippet>WCAG 2.1 Level AA compliance required. Support for screen readers, keyboard navigation, color contrast, text alternatives.</snippet>
      </doc>
    </docs>
    <code>
      <artifact>
        <path>components/ui/Button.tsx</path>
        <kind>component</kind>
        <symbol>Button</symbol>
        <lines>1-50</lines>
        <reason>Button component. Ensure proper ARIA labels, keyboard navigation, focus indicators.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>components/ui/Input.tsx</path>
        <kind>component</kind>
        <symbol>Input</symbol>
        <lines>1-50</lines>
        <reason>Input component. Ensure proper labels, ARIA attributes, error message associations.</reason>
      </artifact>
    </code>
    <dependencies>
      <ecosystem name="node">
        <package name="next" version="^14.2.0" />
        <package name="react" version="^18.3.0" />
        <package name="react-dom" version="^18.3.0" />
        <package name="typescript" version="^5.5.0" />
      </ecosystem>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>

  <constraints>
    <constraint>WCAG compliance: Meet WCAG 2.1 Level AA standards</constraint>
    <constraint>Keyboard navigation: All interactive elements accessible via keyboard, visible focus indicators</constraint>
    <constraint>Screen reader support: Proper ARIA labels, roles, semantic HTML, heading hierarchy</constraint>
    <constraint>Color contrast: Sufficient color contrast ratios (4.5:1 for text, 3:1 for UI components)</constraint>
    <constraint>Text alternatives: Text alternatives for color-coded information, icons, images</constraint>
    <constraint>Form accessibility: Proper labels, error message associations, required field indicators</constraint>
  </constraints>

  <interfaces>
    <interface>
      <name>Accessibility Testing Tools</name>
      <kind>Testing</kind>
      <signature>Use accessibility testing tools:
- axe DevTools (browser extension)
- WAVE (Web Accessibility Evaluation Tool)
- Lighthouse (Chrome DevTools)
- Screen readers (NVDA, JAWS, VoiceOver)
- Keyboard navigation testing</signature>
      <path>All components and pages</path>
    </interface>
  </interfaces>

  <tests>
    <standards>
      Testing approach: Accessibility audits, keyboard navigation tests, screen reader tests, color contrast tests.
      Focus on WCAG 2.1 Level AA compliance, keyboard accessibility, screen reader compatibility, and color contrast.
      Test edge cases: all interactive elements, all forms, all pages, color-coded information.
      Manual testing with screen readers and keyboard navigation.
    </standards>
    <locations>
      Accessibility audits: Use axe DevTools, WAVE, Lighthouse for automated testing
      Keyboard navigation tests: Test all interactive elements via keyboard
      Screen reader tests: Test with NVDA, JAWS, VoiceOver
      Color contrast tests: Verify color contrast ratios meet WCAG standards
      No formal test framework currently configured - focus on manual testing and code review
    </locations>
    <ideas>
      <test id="AC1">
        <description>Test assistive technology support</description>
        <steps>1. Navigate application with assistive technologies. 2. Verify meets WCAG 2.1 Level AA. 3. Verify works with screen readers. 4. Verify keyboard navigation works. 5. Verify text alternatives for colors. 6. Verify clear form labels.</steps>
      </test>
      <test id="AC2">
        <description>Test keyboard navigation</description>
        <steps>1. Navigate using only keyboard. 2. Verify can access all interactive elements. 3. Verify can navigate between sections. 4. Verify can submit forms. 5. Verify can use all features. 6. Verify focus indicators visible.</steps>
      </test>
      <test id="AC3">
        <description>Test screen reader</description>
        <steps>1. Navigate with screen reader. 2. Verify understand page structure. 3. Verify can navigate by headings. 4. Verify understand form labels. 5. Verify understand button purposes. 6. Verify understand error messages.</steps>
      </test>
      <test id="AC4">
        <description>Test color vision deficiency</description>
        <steps>1. View application with color vision deficiency. 2. Verify understand all information without relying on color alone. 3. Verify text alternatives for color-coded information. 4. Verify can distinguish interactive elements.</steps>
      </test>
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>

