<story-context id="bmad/bmm/workflows/4-implementation/story-context" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>4</epicId>
    <storyId>4-5</storyId>
    <title>Bonus Question Tracking</title>
    <status>review</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-11-25</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/stories/4-5-bonus-question-tracking.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>

  <story>
    <asA>Student</asA>
    <iWant>to log bonus questions separately</iWant>
    <soThat>my teacher can see extra work I did</soThat>
    <tasks>
      <task>Verify bonusCount field exists in ProgressLog schema</task>
      <task>Update ProgressLogForm to highlight bonus question field</task>
      <task>Add visual distinction (different background color, icon, or label)</task>
      <task>Update progress display to show bonus separately</task>
      <task>Ensure bonus questions included in progress calculations</task>
      <task>Update progress calculation services to include bonusCount</task>
    </tasks>
  </story>

  <acceptanceCriteria>
    <criterion id="AC1">
      <given>I have completed my assigned questions</given>
      <when>I log bonus questions</when>
      <then>bonus questions are tracked separately</then>
      <and>displayed differently (dark green vs light green)</and>
      <and>included in progress calculations</and>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC2">
      <given>I log bonus questions</given>
      <when>I view my progress</when>
      <then>bonus questions are shown separately from assigned questions</then>
      <and>visual distinction is clear (color coding)</and>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC3">
      <given>bonus questions are logged</given>
      <when>progress is calculated</when>
      <then>bonus questions are included in total progress</then>
      <and>accuracy calculations include bonus questions</and>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC4">
      <given>I view my progress dashboard</given>
      <when>I see question counts</when>
      <then>assigned questions and bonus questions are displayed separately</then>
      <and>total includes both assigned and bonus</and>
    </criterion>
  </acceptanceCriteria>

  <artifacts>
    <docs>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/epics.md</path>
        <title>Epic Breakdown</title>
        <section>Epic 4: Daily Question Logging - Story 4.5</section>
        <snippet>As a Student, I want to log bonus questions separately, So that my teacher can see extra work I did. Bonus question field in logging form, separate tracking in database, visual distinction, progress calculation inclusion.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/PRD.md</path>
        <title>Product Requirements Document</title>
        <section>FR-005: Daily Question Logging</section>
        <snippet>FR-005.5: Students shall be able to log bonus questions separately. Bonus questions are tracked separately, displayed with visual distinction, and included in progress calculations.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/stories/4-2-daily-question-logging-form.md</path>
        <title>Story 4.2: Daily Question Logging Form</title>
        <section>Learnings</section>
        <snippet>ProgressLogForm component created. Form validation and submission patterns established. BonusCount field already exists in schema.</snippet>
      </doc>
    </docs>
    <code>
      <artifact>
        <path>prisma/schema.prisma</path>
        <kind>database schema</kind>
        <symbol>ProgressLog</symbol>
        <lines>121-140</lines>
        <reason>ProgressLog model already has bonusCount field. Verify field is included in API responses and form submission.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>components/student/ProgressLogForm.tsx</path>
        <kind>component</kind>
        <symbol>ProgressLogForm</symbol>
        <lines>1-200</lines>
        <reason>Progress logging form component. Update to highlight bonus question field with visual distinction (different color, icon, or label).</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>components/student/TodaysAssignmentCard.tsx</path>
        <kind>component</kind>
        <symbol>TodaysAssignmentCard</symbol>
        <lines>1-150</lines>
        <reason>Student dashboard component. Update progress display to show bonus questions separately from assigned questions with visual distinction.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>lib/progress-calculator.ts</path>
        <kind>service</kind>
        <symbol>calculateTopicProgress</symbol>
        <lines>1-200</lines>
        <reason>Progress calculation service. Ensure bonusCount is included in total progress and accuracy calculations (denominator includes bonusCount).</reason>
      </artifact>
    </code>
    <dependencies>
      <ecosystem name="node">
        <package name="next" version="^14.2.0" />
        <package name="react" version="^18.3.0" />
        <package name="react-dom" version="^18.3.0" />
        <package name="@prisma/client" version="^5.19.0" />
        <package name="prisma" version="^5.19.0" />
        <package name="typescript" version="^5.5.0" />
      </ecosystem>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>

  <constraints>
    <constraint>Visual distinction: Bonus questions displayed differently (dark green vs light green, or icon, or separate section)</constraint>
    <constraint>Progress calculation: Bonus questions included in total progress: total = right + wrong + empty + bonus</constraint>
    <constraint>Accuracy calculation: Bonus questions included in accuracy denominator: accuracy = (right / (right + wrong + empty + bonus)) × 100</constraint>
    <constraint>Display: Assigned questions and bonus questions displayed separately, total includes both</constraint>
    <constraint>Component pattern: Follow existing component patterns from components/student/ - use TypeScript, Tailwind CSS, proper prop types</constraint>
  </constraints>

  <interfaces>
    <interface>
      <name>ProgressLog Model (with bonusCount)</name>
      <kind>Database model</kind>
      <signature>model ProgressLog {
  id: String @id @default(cuid())
  studentId: String
  assignmentId: String
  date: DateTime @db.Date
  rightCount: Int @default(0)
  wrongCount: Int @default(0)
  emptyCount: Int @default(0)
  bonusCount: Int @default(0) // Bonus questions tracked separately
  ...
}</signature>
      <path>prisma/schema.prisma</path>
    </interface>
  </interfaces>

  <tests>
    <standards>
      Testing approach: Component tests for visual distinction, integration tests for progress calculation including bonus questions.
      Focus on bonus question tracking, visual distinction, and progress calculation correctness.
      Test edge cases: no bonus questions, all bonus questions, bonus questions with assigned questions.
      Manual testing for visual appearance and progress calculation accuracy.
    </standards>
    <locations>
      Component tests: Test ProgressLogForm and TodaysAssignmentCard components for bonus question display
      Integration tests: Test progress calculation including bonus questions
      No formal test framework currently configured - focus on manual testing and code review
    </locations>
    <ideas>
      <test id="AC1">
        <description>Test bonus question tracking</description>
        <steps>1. Log bonus questions (e.g., bonusCount: 10). 2. Verify bonus questions tracked separately. 3. Verify displayed differently (dark green vs light green). 4. Verify included in progress calculations.</steps>
      </test>
      <test id="AC2">
        <description>Test visual distinction</description>
        <steps>1. View progress with bonus questions. 2. Verify bonus questions shown separately from assigned questions. 3. Verify visual distinction is clear (color coding or separate section).</steps>
      </test>
      <test id="AC3">
        <description>Test progress calculation with bonus</description>
        <steps>1. Log progress with bonus questions. 2. Calculate progress. 3. Verify bonus questions included in total progress. 4. Verify accuracy calculations include bonus questions in denominator.</steps>
      </test>
      <test id="AC4">
        <description>Test progress display</description>
        <steps>1. View progress dashboard with bonus questions. 2. Verify assigned questions and bonus questions displayed separately. 3. Verify total includes both assigned and bonus.</steps>
      </test>
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>

